the Pythagorean theorem says that the
area of the square should be equal to
the sum of these two squares but we can
really understand why it's true by
looking at these three triangles the
large green triangle is a reflection of
the original triangle the pink one is a
scaled down copy a similar triangle and
the blue one is similar again because
the triangles are similar these angles
must be equal so we can fit this pink
triangle nicely inside the big one at a
right angle to the hypotenuse
blue triangle works the same way it must
form a right angle with hypotenuse which
means that blue and pink areas must add
to give the original triangle cool right
but how does that prove that the sum of
the squares is equal well remember again
that the smaller triangles are just
scaled down copies of the big one so if
one square is K times the area of one
triangle that factor K must apply to all
squares and triangles and that is enough
to prove that a squared plus b squared
is equal to c squared